Dominique Caron

PhD student, McGill University.

Quantitative Biodiversity Lab, Department of Biology
Stewart Biology Building Office N7/19
1205 Dr. Penfield Avenue
Montréal, Québec, Canada H3A 1B1

dominique.caron@mail.mcgill.ca

(+1) 514-433-2947

GitHub - ORCID - Website

Profile

I am currently completing my PhD in Laura Pollock's lab at McGill University. My thesis focuses on trait-based modeling of trophic interactions of terrestrial vertebrates and the seasonal movements of birds. I am particularly interested in biogeography, biodiversity modeling, and food web ecology. Through my academic and professional experience, I have developed advanced skills in quantitative analyses (R, Julia, QGIS), data management, and ecological modeling.

Education

McGill University

January 2020 - 2024

PhD in Biology

Université de Montréal

September 2017 - December 2018

MSc in Quantitative and Computational Biology

Université de Montréal

September 2014 - May 2017

BSc in Biological Sciences

Polytechnique Montréal

October 2012 - May 2014

B.Eng. in Civil Engineering (unfinished)

Experience

Software Developper , Environment and Climate Change Canada	2019 - 2022
Conservation Planning Assistant, Éco-corridors Laurentiens	2019
MSc Research Intern, Poisot Lab, Université de Montréal	2018
Research Assistant Ouranos Inc.	2018
MSc Research Intern, James Lab, Université de Montréal	2017
Field Assistant, Bélanger Lab, TÉLUQ	2017
Technical Assistant for the Collections of Marine	2016
Invertebrates, Institut québécois de la biodiversité (IQBIO)	

Teaching

Lab Coordinator - Methods in Biology of Organisms, McGill	2023
University.	
Teaching Assistant - Methods in Biology of Organisms, McGill	2021 & 2022
University.	

Teaching Development Fellow - Methods in Biology of Organisms, McGill University.

2020

	Teaching Assistant - Biostatistics I, Université de Montréal. Tutor - Biostatistics I, Université de Montréal. Tutor - Biostatistics II, Université de Montréal.	2018 2018 2018
	rutor - biostatistics 11, omversite de Piontreal.	2010
Grants, Honors, and Awards	Writing-Year Award, Department of Biology, McGill University.	2024
	Graduate Research Ehancement and Travel Award , Department of Biology, McGill University.	2023
	QCBS Excellence Award , Quebec Cener for Biodiversity Science, QCBS.	2023
	Best Poster , Gordon Research Conference on Predictive Ecology, GRC.	2023
	Learning and Development Award (LeaDA) , Quebec Center for Biodiversity Science, QCBS.	2020-2022
	Best Short Presentation, QCBS symposium 2020, QCBS.	2020
	Undergraduate Student Research Award , Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada, NSERC.	2017
	Intensive Courses Award , Quebec Center for Biodiversity Science, QCBS.	2017
	Dean's Honour List , Faculty of Arts and Science, Université de Montréal.	2015 - 2017
Publications	Caron, D., Brose, U., Lurgi, M., Blanchet, F., Gravel, D., & Pollock, L. Trait-matching models predict pairwise interactions across regions, not food web properties. Global Ecology and	2024
	Biogeography, 33(4), e13807. Eckert, I., Brown, A., Caron, D. , Riva, F., & Pollock, L. 30×30 biodiversity gains rely on national coordination. Nature Communications, 14(1), 7113.	2023
	Strydom, T., Bouskila, S., Banville, F., Barros, C., Caron, D. , Farrell, M., Fortin, M.J., Mercier, B., Pollock, L., Runghen, R., Dalla Riva, G., & Poisot, T. Graph embedding and transfer learning can help predict potential species interaction networks despite data limitations. Methods in Ecology and Evolution, 14(12), 2917–2930.	2023
	Caron, D. , Maiorano, L., Thuiller, W., & Pollock, L. Addressing the Eltonian shortfall with trait-based interaction models. Ecology Letters, ele.13966.	2022
	Strydom, T., Bouskila, S., Banville, F., Barros, C., Caron, D. , Farrell, M., Fortin, M.J., Hemming, V., Mercier, B., Pollock, L., Runghen, R., Dalla Riva, G., & Poisot, T. Food web reconstruction through phylogenetic transfer of low-rank network representation. Methods in Ecology and Evolution, 13(12), 2838–2849.	2022
	Strydom, T., Catchen, M., Banville, F., Caron, D. , Dansereau, G., Desjardins-Proulx, P., Forero-Muñoz, N., Higino, G., Mercier, B., Gonzalez, A., Gravel, D., Pollock, L., & Poisot, T. A roadmap towards predicting species interaction networks (across space and time). Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London. Series B, Biological Sciences, 376(1837), 20210063.	2021
	Caron, D. , Lessard, V., Wu, Q., & Poisot, T. (2019). [Re] Insect natural enemies as regulating factors. ReScience, 5(1), #1.	2019

Talks	Caron, D. , Jousse, M., Eckert I., Pollock, L.J. Niche trackers don't play by the rules: Consequences of niche tracking on seasonal north american bird biogeography. QCBS Symposium. Montréal (Canada)	2024
	Caron, D. , Brose, U., Lurgi, M., Blanchet F.G., Gravel, D., Pollock, L.J. Transferability of trophic interaction models across space. GRC on Predictive Ecology. Stonehill College, Massachusetts (USA). Poster	2023
	Caron, D. , Jousse, M., Eckert I., Pollock, L.J. Trophic niche and seasonality shape the structure of avian diversity. Species on the Move conference. Bonita Springs, Florida (USA).	2023
	Caron, D. , Maiorano, L., Thuiller, W., Pollock, L.J. Tackling knowledge gaps about food webs with trait-based models. Ecological Society America (ESA) & Canadian Society for Ecology and Evolution (CSEE) joint meeting. Montréal (Canada).	2022
	Caron, D. What are Muad'Dibs eating? Predicting Dune's metaweb using functional traits. Ecological Society America (ESA) & Canadian Society for Ecology and Evolution (CSEE) joint meeting. Montréal (Canada).	2022
	Caron, D. , Maiorano, L., Thuiller, W., Pollock, L.J. Predicting trophic interactions to fill the Eltonian shortfall. Canadian Society for Ecology and Evolution (CSEE) Annual Meeting. Online	2021
	Caron, D., Pollock, L.J. Doing a lot with "a little": (Re)Building a large food web with sparse data. Colloque du CSBQ. Online	2020
	Caron, D. , Chavaillaz, Y., Roy, P. Évolution d'indicateurs d'exposition à la chaleur et conséquences pour la santé des travailleurs extérieurs. Séminaire Ouranos. Montréal (Canada).	2019
	Caron, D. & James, PMA. L'échelle d'autocorrélation spatiale de données génétiques chez un insecte ravageur de l'Ouest canadien : capacité de dispersion importante et historique de colonisation complexe. Symposium de sciences biologiques de l'Université de Montréal, Montréal (Canada).	2018
	Caron, D. & Poisot, T. Les données ouvertes sur la biodiversité au Québec : forces, faiblesses et défis. Symposium de sciences biologiques de l'Université de Montréal, Montréal (Canada).	2017